Guide to the Henry Wright Papers, 1907-1960, 1907-1938 (bulk)
Wright, Henry papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry Wright papers, 1907-1960, 1907-1938
2736
Henry Wright, 1878-1936.
.9 cubic ft.
Project reports, article notes, and biographical material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes project descriptions and reports on garden cities, housing research; the relation of city planning to architecture; article notes written jointly with Lewis Mumford; and biographical material.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Henry Wright was a city planner.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes project descriptions and reports on garden cities, some of which are with Clarence Stein; housing research, some on war housing and some done with Albert Mayer; the relation of city planning to architecture; article notes written jointly with Lewis Mumford; and biographical material.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wright, Henry, 1878-1936.; Mayer, Albert.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Stein, Clarence S.
Subjects:
Architecture.; City planning.; Housing.; Housing--Effect of wars on.; City planners.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Folders 1-30
  - Biographical data prepared by HW
    - Albert Mayer, "Henry Wright: Creative Planner" Survey Graphic, September 1936 (Box 1)
    - Henry Churchill, "Henry Wright: 1876-1936 " Journal of AIP, November 1960 (Box 1)
    - Benjamin M. Gruzen, "Henry Wright,...A List of References", 1936 (Box 1)
  - A City Plan for Saint Louis (HW was a member of one of the committees), 1907 (Box 1)
  - "Planning Country Home Grounds and Gardens," 4 p. pamphlet, 1909 (Box 1)
  - No Man's Land of Real Estate..., 7 p. manuscript, 1919 (Box 1)
  - "Planning City Areas for Small Homes," Supplement to The Journal of the American Institute of Architects, 16 p., August 1920 (Box 1)
  - Untitled manuscript, 4 p., 1920 (Box 1)
  - "Shall We Community Plan?," The Journal of the American Institute of Architects, 5 p., October 1921 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: To, Lewis Mumford, August 17 with clipping; From, Nebraska Masonic Home, October 8, 1923 (Box 1)
  - "Housing Progress," The Journal of the American Institute of Architects, 2 p. with L.M. [Lewis Mumford?], December 1923 (Box 1)
  - Modern Homes for City Dwellers, 23 p. brochure [mutilated], 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden Cities Studies. A group of 18 studies, drafts and notes relative to the development of garden cities. All listed here because of their subject unity., August 1923-1926 (Box 1)
  - What is to be Learned from Housing Developments of the Past in America, 11 p. typescript, August 13, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Real Estate Development, 3 p. typescript, August 13, 1923 (Box 1)
  - War Housing in the United States, 2 drafts, 7 p. typescript, August 13, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Critical Examination of the Relation of Site Use and Cost to the Housing Problem in America, 15 p. typescript, August 13, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Addenda, 28 p. typescript, August 13, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Further Investigation in the Field of Site Development Costs in Relation to Housing, 5 p. typescript, 6 sheets graphics, August 24, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden City Studies, 7 p. typescript, August 28, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden City Studies, 4 p. typescript, September 3, 1923 (Box 1)
  - A Critical Examination Of Present Zoning Practice in Relation to the Housing Situation, 2 p. typescript, September 3, 1923 (Box 1)
  - [Drafts of Five Sections], 8 p. typescript, "For Mumford,", September 11, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Housing Developments in the Past, 2 drafts, one signed by Lewis Mumford, 16 p. typescript, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden City Reports, Superseded, 40 p. typescript, 16 sheets of graphics, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden City 1st Report, Not Final, 27 p. typescript, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden City Next to Last Report, Not Final, 41 p. typescript; subtitle: Preliminary Study of a Proposed Garden Community in the New York Region by Alexander M. Bing, Henry Wright, Clarence S. Stein. [p. 20 missing], 1923 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 12 p., 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garden Cities, 19 p. manuscript, July 25-28, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Garden Cities, 15 p. typescript, August 5, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Garden City Research, 9 p. typescript, E. Standish Palmer, January-February 1926 (Box 1)
  - First Annual Report of the Stockholders of Associated Specialists, Inc., (HW was First Vice-President), 1924 (Box 1)
  - Report of D.M. Kendall and Henry Wright on their Investigation of the Present Speculative Building Operations now in Progress in Brooklyn and Long Island, 22p. typescript, 19 sheets of graphics and photographs, May 1924 (Box 1)
- Folders 31-49
  - "Exhibit: Preliminary Studies of Natural Features and Economic Development of the State," Commission of Housing and Regional Planning, 8 p. brochure, April 20-25, 1925 (Box 2)
  - "The Road to Good Houses," Survey Graphic, 5 p. issue on planning, May 1925 (Box 2)
  - The Home Ideal Versus Reality, 4 p. typescript, December 15, 1925 (Box 2)
  - "The Home Ideal Versus Reality," American Federationist, 5 p., January 1926 (Box 2)
  - "Housing: How Much for How Much?," The Survey Midmonthly, 5 p., March 15, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Memorandum in regard to proposed regional planning report, 1 p. typescript, March 16, 1926 (Box 2)
  - An Account of Sunnyside Gardens in Relation to Problems and Development of Design and Site Planning..., 21 p. typescript, August 16, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Sunnyside Gardens an Experiment in Planning, 10 p. typescript, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Study of Application of Sunnyside Planning Principles to a Larger City Area, 23 p. typescript and graphics, 1926 (Box 2)
  - [C.A. Beard], "Economy, Charm and Safety of the Cul-de-Sac Street," The American City, 4 p. [The author, identified as an "eminent English town planner," comments on Radburn.], Nov. 1928 (Box 2)
  - Untitled typescript, 17 p., annotated "AIA C.P.C.", 1928 (Box 2)
  - "Group Housing," Building Developer, 8 p., August 1929 (Box 2)
  - "How to Reduce the Cost of Land Development," National Real Estate Journal, 6 p., September 2, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Some Principles Relating to the Economics of Land Subdivision," American City Planning Institute, 12 p. Preprint No. 1, Nov. 1929 (Box 2)
  - Some Principles Relating to the Economics of Land Subdivision, Paper No. 1. 20 p. pamphlet including the article above and comment on it by members of the Institute, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Housing Research Completed under the Direction of Henry Wright, 84 p. typescript and 11 sheets of graphics, January-April 1930 (Box 2)
  - Housing Research, Division II Only, The Problems and Relative Advantages of Smaller Types of Dwellings..., 56 p. typescript and 10 pages of graphics, January-April 1930 (Box 2)
  - "Picturesque Architecture," The Architecture Forum, 7 p., February 1931 (Box 2)
  - "The Place of the Apartment in the Modern Community," The Architectural Record, 31 p., plus 6 p. multilith, March 1930 (Box 2)
  - "The Autobiography of Another Idea," reprint from The Western Architect, 7 p., September 1930 (Box 2)
- Folders 50-92
  - Discussion of Neighborhood Planning..., 6 p. typescript, January 17, 1931 (Box 3)
  - "The Architect, the Plan and the City," The Architectural Forum, 7 p., February 1931 (Box 3)
  - "The Apartment House: A Review and Forecast," The Architectural Record, 16 p., March 1931 (Box 3)
  - The President’s Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership. Tentative Report of the Committee on Subdivision Layout. 82 p. pamphlet, [HW was a member of the committee], December 3, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Proceedings: Committee on Design of the President's Conference Home Building and Home Ownership, 33 p. typescript, December 3, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Summary of Further Developments of "A Housing Research" for the Consideration of the Temporary Housing Commission of Illinois, 81 p. typescript, 1931 (Box 3)
  - The In Betweens of Community Planning, Student Memo: Lecture Series, 3 p. multilith, February 15, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Will a New Dwelling Type Solve the Problem of Providing Low Rentals for the Lower-Income Groups?, 4 p. multilith, March 12, 1932 (Box 3)
  - "The Cost of Housing," The Architectural Forum, 6 p., March 1932 (Box 3)
  - Memorandum, To Clarence S. Stein, 3 p., April 7, 1932 (Box 3)
  - "A Self - Starter for the Building Industry," Building Investment, 6 p., June 1932 (Box 3)
  - "Hillside Group Housing," The Architectural Record, 14 p., October 1932 (Box 3)
  - Hillside Housing Development, Memorandum to Clarence S. Stein, 7 p., October 29, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Summary and Further Development...Temporary Housing Commission of Illinois, 82 p. typescript, [See item in 1931], 1932 (Box 3)
  - "Are We Ready for an American Housing Advance?," Architecture, 8 p., June 1933 (Box 3)
  - "Housing-Where, When, and How?," Architecture, 32 p., forward by Lewis Mumford, July 1933 (Box 3)
  - "Housing - Where, When, and How?," Part Two, 31 p., August 1933 (Box 3)
  - "Sinking Slums," Survey Graphic, 3 p., August 1933 (Box 3)
  - Notes to Lewis Mumford re: New Republican Articles. 8 p. typescript, January 22, 1934 (Box 3)
  - "New Homes for a New Deal," 46 p. pamphlet, with Albert Mayer and Lewis Mumford, February 14, 1934 (Box 3)
  - "New Homes for a New Deal, Part II Abolishing Slums Forever," 4 p. article from The New Republic, Feb. 21, 1934. "Part IV A Concrete Program," 4 p., March 7, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Questions Relating to Slum Clearance and Low Cost Housing Problems, 9 p. typescript, August 31, 1934 (Box 3)
  - "Housing Conditions in Relation to Scientific Machine Production," The Journal of the Franklin Institute, 13 p. reprint, October 1934 (Box 3)
  - Memorandum with respect to report of recent tour of European housing experts... 2 p. typescript, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Article No. 1, 10 p. typescript, relates to New Deal housing, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Article No. 2, 11 p. typescript, relates to New Deal housing, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Oscar Fisher, "Buckingham: Housing Laboratory," The Architectural Record, 18 p. reprint. "One of Henry Wright's last designs...," 2 other items Re: Buckingham, 1938 (Box 3)
  - To Plan or Not to Plan, 7 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Article re: problem of subdivisions, 5 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Some Lesson on the Land Sub-Division Problem, 6 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Confidential to Housing board Advising Committee, 13 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - The Public Interest in Good Housing, 7 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Town Planning in the United States, 5 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - The Fallacy of High Buildings: A Swing of the Pendulum, 8 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - The Architect and Prosperity, 6 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Land Subdivision, 17 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Queens-Astoria: A Study in Realistic City Planning, 3 p. typescript with Carol Aronovici, Henry S. Churchill, William Lescraze, Albert Mayer (Box 3)
  - Wanted a Subdividion for the Gridiron Street System, 3 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Too Much Planning or Too Many Plans? 5 p. typescript fragment (Box 3)
  - Outline of a book, 15 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - A.I.A. Talk - Wednesday Afternoon, 4 p. typescript (Box 3)
  - Fragment of article comparing Radburn and Wyandotte, Michigan, 2 p. typescript (Box 3)